# **Enrico Foglia**

#### MLOPS - BACKEND DEVELOPMENT - DATA SCIENCE

Passionate about machine learning, data and programming. Experienced in ML modelling, MLOps, development of APIs and containerized microservice architectures in the Cloud. Enthusiastic about learning new tools, programming languages and methodologies.

#### Reach me at:



Saronno, VA



+39 3534035024



enrico.foglia@hotmail.com



linkedin: /efoglia



github.com/Enrico4444/



www.researchgate.net/profile/Enrico



### **Education**

University of Salford, UK, 2018-2019 Master Degree (MSc) Data Science Distinction

University of Westminster, UK, 2012-2016 Bachelor Degree (BSc), Psychology First Class Honours



## **Certifications**

- · AWS Machine Learning Engineer (in progress)
- Azure Cloud Data Fundamentals (DP
- Azure Cloud Data Scientist (DP 100)
- · SAS Student Academy Certification



#### **Selected Courses**

- · Analisi I Politecnico di Milano
- · Algebra Lineare Politecnico di Milano
- · Principi di Informatica Politecnico di
- · REST APIs with Flask & Python Udemy
- Machine Learning Specialization -
- · Sequence Models Coursera



# **Work Experience**

#### NTTData Italia, Milano, Italy

Data Scientist (consultant) - 01/2021 - currently

Worked with clients to deliver Machine Learning, MLOps and Data Engineering solutions, with strong focus on Cloud and Microservice architectures. Also responsible for the Partnership and Certification programs within the company

#### LOGIVAN, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam

Data Scientist - 06/2019 - 01/2021

Modelling and deployment of two ML models, a price prediction model and a recommender system, that critically impacted the activity of this logistics startup in terms of increased automation and reduced costs. Worked in a fast-paced startup environment.

#### Opus Energy, London, UK

Data Scientist (intern) - 02/2019 - 05/2019 Developed an energy consumption forecasting POC

#### University of East London, London, UK

**Research Analyst** - 06/2016 - 09/2016

Written a published systematic review on dehydration in the elderly

#### University of Westminster, London, UK

**Research Analyst** - 01/2016 - 05/2016

Conducted a cognitive study on Theory of Mind in the adolescents

#### King's College London, London, UK

Research Analyst (intern) - 09/2014 - 12/2015 Published research papers on cannabis and psychosis

# Selected Work Projects

ML Pipelines on AWS - 01/2022 - currently

Role **AWS Specialist, Data Engineer** Company NTTDATA - client: energy company

**Tools** AWS, SageMaker, SQS, Spark, Sqoop, HDFS, Python, Scala, Bitbucket, Bamboo

Description Data transfer from relational DB to S3 with Sqoop; optimization of Spark

> processing of millions of records in terms of cost and time reduction; deployment on SageMaker with StepFunctions and Lambdas; publication of predictions

through SQS message broker

MLOps software development - 07/2021 - 01/2022

Backend Developer, MLOps Role Company

NTTDATA - client: bank

Python, Flask, Nginx, UWSGI, SQL, MinIO, Docker, Kubernetes, GitLab **Tools** 

Description Developed backend in Python of MLOps software that allows automation of ML pipelines through management, catalog, retraining and monitoring of machine

learning models. REST API deployed as containerized microservice on

Kubernetes cluster.

# Publications

- Author of patent for Recommender System for Logistics (owner: LOGIVAN)
- Publications in the field of Psychology: www.researchgate.net/profile/Enrico\_ Foglia/contributions



### Conferences

- TopDev Vietnam Speaker 2019: Presented my work on Recommender Systems
- Barcamp Vietnam Speaker 2019: Presented my work on Recommender **Systems**
- · Uk-Vietnam Research Link, IOT workshop - 2018
- · Schizophrenia International Research Society - Conference Poster Presentation - 2016

# Languages

- Italian (native)
- English (fluent)
- · Spanish (basic)

MLOps software development - 04/2021 - 07/2021

Role Backend Developer, MLOps Company NTTDATA - client: energy company

**Tools** Azure Cloud, Python, RabbitMQ, Docker, MinIO, Postgres Description

Developed backend in Python of MLOps software. Implementation tailored to fit client's architecture (deployment on Azure Kubernetes cluster, asyncronous communication among microservice through message broker - RabbitMQ). In

addition, created Python packages deployed on Azure Artifacts

NLP - Cognitive Search - 01/2021 - 03/2021

**Data Scientist & Backend Developer** Role Company NTTDATA - client: gas company

Python, Scala, Flask, MongoDB, Docker, GitLab Tools

Description Developed a cognitive search engine based on Word Embeddings using

Word2Vec. Optimized Search speed through Locality Sensitive Hashing (LSH) implemented in Python and MongoDB aggregation language, and using MongoDB

sharding. Flask API deployed within microservice architecture.

Price Prediction for Logistics Orders - 06/2020 - 12/2020

**Data Scientist & Backend Developer** Role

LOGIVAN Company

AWS, Python, Keras, Flask, Docker, GitLab, AWS, Redis **Tools** 

Prediction of winning price for any bidding made by suppliers to win logistics Description

orders, with an average percentage error of 15%. Built a fully-connected neural network with embeddings using Keras. Deployed Flask API on AWS EC2

containerized with Docker.

Recommender System for Freight Matching - 07/2019 - 06/2020

**Data Scientist & Backend Developer** Role

**LOGIVAN** Company

AWS, Python, Keras, Flask, Docker, GitLab, AWS, Redis Tools

Identification of the most suitable suppliers for logistics orders through a Description

> Recommender System. Recommendation task re-framed as binary classification with F1-score of 0.8. Adopted a siamese neural network with embeddings and triplet loss function with triplet mining techniques, as inspired by Google FaceNet (Schroff et al., 2015). Deployed Flask API on AWS EC2 containerized with

Docker. The algorithm was patented.

Half-hourly Energy Consumption Forecasting - 01/2019 - 03/2019

**Data Scientist** Role **Opus Energy** Company

Python, AWS Sagemaker **Tools** 

Description Half-hourly consumption profiles of new customers with no historical consumption

data were estimated through a regression model based on customer

characteristics. This POC slightly outperformed the standard UK Consumption

Profile Classes traditionally used to categorize new customers.

Big Data analysis for Security Threats Identification - 03/2018 - 04/2018

**Data Scientist** 

MSc Coursework Role

Company Hadoop, Spark, Impala, PySpark, Scala, HDFS, Sqoop

**Tools** Millions of twitter feeds analysed for timing and amount to identify security Description threats during football matches, using Hadoop ecosystem (Spark, Impala, HDFS,

Sqoop)

SQL Database Design for Email Marketing - 01/2018 - 02/2018

Role SQL Developer
Company MSc Coursework
Tools SQL, SSMS, SSIS

Description Designed database for email marketing using SQL Server Management Studio (SSMS). Followed DB design principles (normalization, lookup tables, constraints, isolation in concurrency control, atomicity and consistency in transaction

management). Complex stored procedures and triggers allowed a variety of actions (subscribe, unsubscribe, etc.) and tracking of user metrics (timing of user behaviour, geomapping, etc.). Bulk actions such as bulk subscription enabled using SSIS. Full, differential and transaction-log backups implemented. DB security ensured through authorization and authentication methods.



# **Selected Personal Projects**

#### Full-stack Web App Development (in progress)

Github: github.com/Enrico4444/DbSearch/

Tool that, given a database schema, allows user to insert data, import tables from excel, search tables through a UI with AND / OR operators, and view combined data from multiple tables. Developed to demonstrate mastery of all aspects of wed development.

- Python API (Flask + UWSGI + Nginx) Backend
- Angular Frontend (to be done)
- Postgres DB and MinIO object storage
- Security and User managment with JWT
- Kubernetes deployment (to be done)
- AWS deployment (<u>to be done</u>)
- CI/CD in Jenkins (to be done)

#### ML Algorithms from scratch

Github: github.com/Enrico4444/AlgosFromScratch

ML and Deep Learning algorithms coded from scratch in numpy, to learn and apply mathematics behind each model



### **Technical Stack**

Experienced Inte	rmediate - Basic
------------------	------------------

Programming langPythonScala, C++, RCloudAWSAzure

Databses SQL - any dialect, MongoDB

Shell scriptingBashPowerShellML frameworksTensorflow, SpacyPyTorch

OS Windows, Linux

CI/CD & DevOps GitLab Jenkins, Bitbucket, Bamboo

**Containers** Docker Kubernetes

Others MinIO